Guide to the Thomas W. Streeter Collection of Hudson Book Company, Edward Eberstadt, and Edward Eberstadt & Sons Catalogs
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Thomas W. Streeter collection of Hudson Book Company, Edward Eberstadt, and Edward Eberstadt & Sons catalogs
1929-1965
WA MSS S-2588
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
2.92
(7 boxes)
Collection consists of Thomas W. Streeter's annotated copies of sale and exhibition catalogs issued by New York City rare book dealer Edward Eberstadt (1883-1958) and his sons, Lindley and Charles, during their careers as antiquarian booksellers. The collection includes more than 90 catalogs, announcements, and sales lists issued by three businesses-- the Hudson Book Company, Edward Eberstadt, and Edward Eberstadt & Sons-- between 1929 and 1965.
Streeter, Thomas W. (Thomas Winthrop), 1883-1965
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Michael D. Heaston, 2006
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
THOMAS W. STREETER (1883-1965)
Thomas W. Streeter (1883-1965), lawyer and businessman, is known for his Bibliography of Texas and his work in the field of Americana. Born in Concord, New Hampshire, on July 20, 1883, Streeter graduated from St. Paul's School in Concord in 1900, and subsequently earned degrees from Dartmouth College (B.L., 1904) and Harvard Law School (LL.B., 1907). Streeter began practicing law in Boston and married Ruth Cheney in 1917. The couple had four children.
In 1917 Streeter moved to New York and began a career in business and finance. He eventually became president of the American International Corporation. Though Streeter retired from active business in 1939 to devote himself to collecting Americana, his interest in early American history and collecting was already established. While serving as chairman of the board of Simms Petroleum Corporation from 1923 to 1930, he took advantage of business trips to Texas to locate and acquire materials relating to Texas history. In 1936 rare items from his collection were exhibited at the Texas Centennial in Dallas and in 1939, his collection was showcased at the opening of the San Jacinto Monument and Museum. Streeter published a bibliography of selected items from his collection in 1952, titled Americana-Beginnings. Over the next five years, Streeter published the five-volume Bibliography of Texas, 1795-1845. After completing the exhaustive work, he sold his Texas collection to Yale University's Collection of Western Americana.
As reflected in Americana-Beginnings, Streeter collected extensively in many areas of American history. Before his death, which occurred in Morristown, New Jersey, on June 12, 1965, Streeter developed plans to auction most of his personal collection. The auction took place in 7 sales at Parke-Bernet Galleries, New York City, between October 25, 1966, and October 22, 1969. The catalog for the sale, titled "The celebrated collection of Americana formed by the late Thomas Winthrop Streeter..." was based on Streeter's notes about his books.
Scope and Contents
The Thomas W. Streeter Collection of Hudson Book Company, Edward Eberstadt, and Edward Eberstadt & Sons Catalogs consists of more than 90 Americana-related book catalogs, supplements, sales lists, and exhibition catalogs issued by New York City rare book dealer Edward Eberstadt (1883-1958) and his sons, Lindley and Charles, between 1929 and 1965. The Eberstadt companies represented in the collection are the Hudson Book Company, Edward Eberstadt, and Edward Eberstadt & Sons. Thomas Streeter lightly annotated many of the catalogs in this collection, both listing on the cover and marking inside the catalogs items of interest, as well as occasionally correcting or supplementing the text. His penciled handwritten dates are the basis for the bracketed supplied dates in the box and folder listing.
Series I, Catalogs, (Boxes 1-7) contains publications by three of the Eberstadts' bookselling companies and is organized into 3 subseries: Hudson Book Company, Edward Eberstadt, and Edward Eberstadt & Sons. Within each subseries, numbered publications are listed first in ascending order. Unnumbered publications follow. Many of the catalogs are general lists of Americana items, but some were based around particular geographical or historical themes. Publication titles have been transcribed. The collection includes a number of advance copies of catalogs, as well as two exhibition catalogs that Edward Eberstadt & Sons published in 1958 for exhibitions at the Fort Worth Art Center and the Dallas Public Library.
Series II, Other Material, (Box 7) consists of a few clippings related to Edward Eberstadt & Sons's 1941 publication of Northwest Coast (Catalog No. 119), as well as a stapled handmade booklet titled "A Few 'Kind Words'", containing photostat reproductions of letters from rare book librarians offering congratulations to the firm on the fine quality of their work.
Americana -- Bibliography -- Catalogs; Booksellers' catalogs -- New York (State) -- New York; Manuscripts, American -- Catalogs; Sales catalogs; Bibliographers, American; Eberstadt, Edward, 1883-1958; Streeter, Thomas W. (Thomas Winthrop), 1883-1965; Edward Eberstadt & Sons -- Catalogs; Edward Eberstadt (Firm) -- Catalogs; Hudson Book Company -- Catalogs
- Catalogs, Series I; 2.92; (7 boxes)
  - HUDSON BOOK COMPANY
    - Numbered
      - Nos. 26-28, "Americana", n.d. (Box 1, Folder 1-3)
      - No. 75, "Americana", n.d. (Box 1, Folder 4)
      - No. 76, "Early West - Far West Indians and the Overland Trail" (Box 1, Folder 5)
      - No. 77, "A Catalogue of Rare and Standard Books on The South, The Southwest, The Early West and The Far West" (Box 1, Folder 6)
      - No. 78, "Americana", n.d. (Box 1, Folder 7)
      - No. 79, Part II, "Americana", n.d. (Box 1, Folder 8)
      - Nos. 80-81, "Americana", n.d. (Box 1, Folder 9-10)
      - No. 82, "A Special Plum-Pudding of Americana, Being a Most Unusual LIst of Out-of-the Way Books, Pamphlets, and Maps" (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Unnumbered
      - "How They Went West! Pioneer Narratives of the Overland Trail" (Box 1, Folder 12)
      - "Western Americana", n.d. (Box 1, Folder 13)
      - "West O' The Rockies", n.d. (Box 1, Folder 14)
      - "When the West Was New! Source Books of the "Wild & Wooley"", n.d. (Box 1, Folder 15)
      - "[...] Local History", n.d. (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - EDWARD EBERSTADT
    - Nos. 91-94, "Americana", 1929-1930 (Box 2, Folder 17-20)
    - Nos. 101-102, "Americana", 1935 (Box 2, Folder 21-22)
    - No. 104, "Americana Part Two", 1936 (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - No. 105, "Americana Part Three" (two copies), 1936 (Box 2, Folder 24-25)
    - No. 107, "Americana Part Five", 1937 (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - No. 109, "A Catalogue of Books Relating to America", 1937 (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - No. 110, "Rare Americana" (two copies), 1937 (Box 2, Folder 28-29)
    - Advance List 1-3, "Western Americana", 1931 (Box 2, Folder 30-32)
    - Advance List 4-7, "Americana", n.d. (Box 2, Folder 33-36)
  - EDWARD EBERSTADT & SONS
    - Numbered
      - Nos. 111-113, "Americana", 1938 (Box 3, Folder 37-41)
        Scope and Contents
        Two Copies of No. 112 and 113.
      - Nos. 114-115, "Americana", 1939-1940 (Box 3, Folder 42-45)
        Two Copies of No. 114 and 115.
      - List Nos. 116-118, "Americana", 1940 (Box 3, Folder 46)
      - No. 119, "The Northwest Coast" (2 copies, hardcover and softcover), 1941 (Box 4, Folder 47-48)
        Soft cover accompanied by "Some Advance Comment on The Northwest Coast" pamphlet.
        Related Archival Materials note
        See also: Box 7, folder 93
      - No. 120, "Apache - Land", 1942 (Box 4, Folder 49)
      - No. 121, "Americana, The Land We Love", 1942 (Box 4, Folder 50)
      - No. 122, "Indian Captives and Massacres", 1943 (Box 4, Folder 51)
      - No. 123, "Americana", 1947 (Box 4, Folder 52)
      - No. 124, "Yosemite and the California Big Tree,", 1949 (Box 4, Folder 53)
      - No. 125, "Books of the California Gold Rush 1849", 1949 (Box 4, Folder 54)
      - No. 126, "Americana", 1950 (Box 4, Folder 55)
      - Nos. 127-128, "Americana", 1950-1951 (Box 4, Folder 56-58)
        Two Copies of No. 128.
      - No. 129, "American Historical Documents &, Manuscripts" (Box 4, Folder 59)
      - Nos. 130-131, "Americana", 1952-1953 (Box 5, Folder 60-63)
        Three Copies of No. 131.
      - Nos. 132-133, "Americana", 1953-1954 (Box 5, Folder 64-66)
        Two Copies of No. 132.
      - No. 133, "Americana", 1954 (Box 5, Folder 67)
        Advance hardcover copy, accompanied by letter.
      - Nos. 134-136, "Americana", 1954-1955 (Box 5, Folder 68-70)
        No. 135, advance hardcover copy.
      - No. 137, "Kansas and the Great Plains", 1955 (Box 6, Folder 71)
      - No. 138, "Americana", 1956 (Box 6, Folder 72)
        Advance copy.
      - No. 139, "A Distinguished Collection of Western Paintings", [1956] (Box 6, Folder 73)
      - No. 140, "Americana", [1957] (Box 6, Folder 74)
      - [No. 141?], "Utah and the Mormans", [1956] (Box 6, Folder 75)
      - [No. 143?], "Indian Treaties", [1956] (Box 6, Folder 76)
      - No. 146, "American Paintings: Historical, Genre, Western", 1958 (Box 6, Folder 77)
      - No. 148, "Alaska and the Northwest Coast", [1959] (Box 6, Folder 78)
      - Nos. 152-157, "Americana", [1960-1961] (Box 6, Folder 79)
      - No. 158, "California Delineated", 1962 (Box 6, Folder 80)
      - No. 160, "Americana", 1963 (Box 6, Folder 81)
      - No. 161, "Western America in Documents", 1963 (Box 6, Folder 82)
      - No. 162, "Texas", 1963 (Box 6, Folder 83)
      - No. 164, "Americana", 1964 (Box 7, Folder 84)
      - No. 166, "American Constitutions", 1964 (Box 7, Folder 85)
      - Nos. 167-168, "Americana", 1965 (Box 7, Folder 86-87)
    - Unnumbered
      - "Americana, Special Quotation List "A", [1948 Mar] (Box 7, Folder 88)
      - "Americana, Special Quotation List "B", [1948 Mar] (Box 7, Folder 89)
      - "Books of the Gold Rush," annotated typescript, 1949 Mar 1 (Box 7, Folder 90)
      - "The History of Texas As Spanish Colony, Mexican State and Independent Republic," exhibition catalog, 1958 (Box 7, Folder 91)
      - "19th Century Painters of the Southwest," loan exhibition catalog, 1958 Apr 14-May 4 (Box 7, Folder 92)
- Other Materials, 1941; Series II
  - "A Few Kind Words," booklet accompanied by clippings, 1941 (Box 7, Folder 93)